This week on the Computer Chronicles,
a hands on demo of Windows 95.
A visit to the Win95 launch
with Bill Gates and Jay Leno.
Some advice on how to learn how to use
the new version of Windows, a sneak
preview of two new Win95 applications,
a guide to online help for Windows 95,
and this week's Computer News.
All coming up next on the Computer Chronicles.
Computer Chronicles is made possible in
part by Hewlett Packard, working with
industry leaders to ensure compatibility
across the board and across the network.
HPPCs, you're looking at
partnership in a whole new light.
The Computer Chronicles is also made
possible by the Software Publishers
Association, providers of educational
materials to help manage software.
Don't copy that floppy.
Hi and welcome to the Computer Chronicles,
I'm Stuart Chafay.
Unless you've been asleep somewhere for
the last few months, you no doubt know
that Windows 95 is upon us.
Several million people have already bought
the Win95 upgrade, but most computer
users are still thinking about it.
Should you buy it? Is it worth the 89 bucks?
And how will your PC life be better
if you have Windows 95?
These are the questions we'll
try to answer for you today.
First of all, let's take a look at some
of the features of Windows 95, and for
that we brought in an expert,
Joe Fabris of Microsoft.
Alright, here's Win95, and obviously first
of all it looks different, I don't see
my usual program manager in my little windows.
Tell me what's going on here.
Well we combine the program manager and
the file manager into a single uniform
desktop, and that's what we see here,
where I've got an icon representing my
computer and all its peripherals,
network connection, and other folders and icons
that I can add as I customize it.
Alright, so the big thing is bottom left,
the start button, which is kind of
intuitive, I want to start doing something,
so I click on start, and show me
how I launch a program in Win95.
Sure, if you click on the start button,
you'll find there is an icon
called the programs over here.
This is where everything that you had
in your old program manager has gone to
when you start Windows for the
first time under Windows 95.
Alright, and that first window that opens up,
I can customize that too and
determine what will show up when I click start,
right?
Exactly,
everything above the program is a customization
that I've done prior to coming in today.
Alright, so I want to run a program,
so I drill down there in the menus.
And I'll go over to Microsoft Office,
this is Office for Windows 95, and I'll
launch Excel simply by clicking on it one time.
Alright, so Excel is up and running now,
and what happens if I want to run a
second program, or I want to do
something else while Excel is running?
That's one thing that Windows has
always been good at,
and now it's gotten better.
In fact, this time what I like to do
is instead of trying to go find an
application and run a document, I like to
find a document and run an application.
So I'll go over here to the documents menu
on the start button, which keeps track
of the last 15 or so applications that you ran,
and I'll go here.
So in fact, the last 15 things I did,
regardless of what application, was not
just in Excel or not just in Word.
Right, and it doesn't matter whether
it was on your machine or on a network
drive, it'll go and find it.
So you want to open that memo.
Right, so now that's going to go find Word,
launch Word, and
then get the document and open it together.
Alright, now I've got both things running,
if I want to go back to Excel and
click on Excel, Word disappears.
Now that's a problem you fixed
basically from the old Windows.
Right, our usability lab showed that when
people would go click on something like
Excel here, Word would vanish from the
screen and they had no idea where it was.
Should I open it up and running,
or should I open it again?
Exactly. That's why we've added at the
bottom of the screen something called the
task bar, which keeps track of all
the applications you have running.
So if I can go back to Word now by
clicking on it on the task bar.
Okay, let's talk about file management
now and how I do things like copy
files and move files in Win95.
Okay, I'll go back to the start
button and I'll click on my computer.
And now we'll get that view I set up
on my peripherals and here we say I
have a floppy drive and my hard drive.
Now let's move some files from the
floppy drive, so I'll double click here
and I'll just choose all of these items.
And now I'm going to drag
them over to my hard disk.
So you can just drag and
drop and do it that way.
Right, and I use the second mouse button
on Windows and here I have some options.
I can move them, I can copy them,
or I can create a shortcut.
And a shortcut would leave the original
files where they were, but just put an
icon there so I could go to a place where
I often go for a shortcut, launch the
application and it could be on a network drive
somewhere else or it could
be on a floppy drive.
But that's what a shortcut does.
I'll just do a quick copy over there.
Okay, now there's another thing when
I go in the store looking for Windows
95 called Microsoft Plus.
What does Plus add to Win95?
Okay, when you saw when we started how
I had that nice Windows background
with my icons looking a certain way.
The Plus has a lot of things and I'm
going to focus on the fun things.
And if I go to the control panel,
we have a new icon added here when the Plus
gets installed called Desktop Themes.
And if I launch this, we'll see that I
can now change the way my screen and my
computer looks and I can have it fit
sort of my mood and have some pre-built
themes that Microsoft's put together
with some graphic artists like Dangerous
Creatures or Leonardo da Vinci.
I was down at the hate district last
night visiting my sister and this
one called the 60s reminds me of that.
So if I'm in that mood today,
I can click on that and have it on the screen.
So you can sort of customize
your desktop day by day
depending on what you feel like.
Exactly.
Design your desktop.
And what it'll do is it'll
change the background
to something that looks like the 60s.
And then we'll see new icons.
I have a peace sign from my computer and
beads for the network neighborhood and
all my sounds now changed as well.
Alright, now Plus, a lot of people are
getting Plus because it comes with a
pretty cool 3D pinball game, right?
Can we see what that looks like?
I'll launch the pinball game right now
and you'll see a nice pinball table.
And we'll start a game up.
We'll have all the pinball
sounds that we expect.
And you'll see some pretty good
graphic animation that's getting an
improvement in Windows 95 as well.
Okay, let's get out of this and
let me ask you about autoplay.
Now another feature in here is if
you've got a CD-ROM drive, what, it
automatically launches
whatever CD you stick in?
Exactly.
In fact, I've got one right here
that I picked up the other day.
And this is a music CD that
I bought at Tower Records.
And when I put it in, the machine
automatically detects that I put a CD in.
And now it'll launch the
application that plays music and
it'll start the songs that are on this disc.
So it not only detects you put a CD in,
but it knows it's a music CD and so it's
going to launch the audio player program,
whatever that is.
Not the CD-ROM.
Exactly.
And this is a new piece of Microsoft
music you guys own now, I guess.
Well, we're having some fun with it.
Yes, we are.
Okay, thank you very much, Joe.
It's been my pleasure.
Okay, Windows 95 is after all just an
operating system and a user interface, but
the launch of the product was choreographed,
more like a Hollywood movie
premiere than a software title.
In case you missed it, here's what it
was like in Redmond, Washington the day
Windows 95 was finally released.
Ladies and gentlemen, Jay Leno.
[...]
No, it's not the Tonight Show. Bill Gates
invited Jay Leno to launch Windows 95
at this Hollywood-style event
at Microsoft headquarters.
Well, Windows 95 is so easy,
even a talk show host can figure it out.
Hello! Hello!
You got your task bar?
Let's go right down there.
Little task bar there, you can click on there,
you see, and I can change my mind.
Do I go over here? This one too.
I can change my mind faster
than Bill Clinton. Look at that, huh?
Health care, no health care.
Republican today, Democrat tomorrow.
Sure, there you go.
Flip it back and forward, back and forward.
Easy as pie
-ola. That's a technical term, Pius.
There were video testimonials by
corporate users as well as home users.
I take the CD, put it in,
click it on the pewter, and the big circle
comes, and then the bird comes.
Members of the audience were pulled
backstage to upgrade from Windows 3.1 to
Windows 95 during the gala.
The site was connected via satellite to
an audience in an amusement park in the
Silicon Valley,
and the now widely recognized Start
Me Up commercial previewed here.
The big screen came down to
reveal the development team.
The audience made its way past them to the
circus tents filled with more than 300
applications developed for Windows 95.
For the Computer Chronicles, I'm Giles Bateman.
Now you've all heard the horror stories
about what you're going to have to spend
to run Windows 95.
More RAM, bigger hard drive,
new keyboard, maybe a processor upgrade.
Let's try to figure out what you really do
need to run the new version of Windows.
Here to help us out, a syndicated columnist,
author, and all-around PC
expert Larry Magid. Welcome, Larry.
Thank you.
Before we get to the toys here,
let's talk about installing Windows 95.
What should you do to your PC
before you start to install it?
Well, the first thing you should do
is back up and very leaf back up your
important data files because
those you can't replace.
You can never tell what's going
to happen during the install.
Absolutely. You never know,
even though most of the time it goes fine.
The next thing you want to do is get
rid of any viruses you might have.
Make sure you've got a nice clean system.
Disable any of your TSRs or anything
that's kind of quirky so that when the
Windows 95 installation program starts running,
it's got a fairly
vanilla ordinary system to deal with.
Then, after you've done all that,
make sure you've got plenty of space in
your hard drive because that's critical.
Windows 95 is going to use every
nook and cranny you've got.
Let's talk about that.
First of all,
let's talk RAM before we talk hard drive.
We hear that you really
can't run Windows 95 if you
have a 4-megabyte machine, right?
In theory, you can, but then a family of four
could live in a one-bedroom apartment,
theoretically.
In reality, whatever the rules
were for Windows 3.1, you doubled.
The rule of Windows 3.
1, 4 megs minimum, Windows 95 for all practical
purposes, 8 megabytes is your minimum system.
If you want a really nice system with
plenty of room to grow, 16 megabytes
is really excellent.
That's what I use.
If you're a heavy power user and you've
got a lot of CAD-CAM or big graphic
images, then you probably want to go
to 32 megabytes, believe it or not.
That's what the power users
are doing these days.
Let's talk about the RAM upgrade options,
and we have a couple of them over here.
First of all, this PC MCIA card.
I guess if you have a laptop and you have a
PC slot, you can just stick that in there.
Absolutely.
If you get an extra slot and you can afford
it, that's a great easy way to do it.
Okay. Now, sometimes you don't have a slot,
and I guess these
are sort of little mini-SIM.
Usually there's a little
door in the back of your
laptop, and you turn it off and plug those in.
They're pretty easy to
install when they do the job.
For the typical desktop user, you've got
your regular PC. This is the normal...
Right. You can get up to 16 megabytes
of memory on one of these little...
They're called a SIM modular,
and they just plug right into the
motherboard,
and they're fairly easy to install.
If you know how to take your computer apart, if
you're comfortable, you can do it yourself.
If you're not, it's a 10-footer.
Let's do that right here.
We have a PC open, and we'll just lift this
power supply and get it out of the way.
And these are your RAM slots right in here,
right?
That's right, and you'd have an empty one,
and you just pop it in there and clip
it down and turn it on the
machine if all goes well.
You've got to do memory.
You're not going to be afraid to do that.
No. The only thing is make sure you
touch the chassis to discharge any
electricity or the static you may before
you touch one of these components.
Other than that, you're fine.
Let's get back to the hard
drive issue you mentioned.
Windows 9 eVive takes up a lot
of space on your hard drive.
Most of us don't have a lot of
space left over on our hard drive.
What are the options then
to get more hard drives?
Well, of course, you could always buy another
hard drive,
and eventually you can do compression.
But the main thing you want to do
is like cleaning out your garage.
You probably have more space than you realize.
If you probably have a lot of junk on
your machine, programs that you haven't
used in months, go ahead and delete them.
And then you get into the issue,
how do you delete them?
Well, if you really know what you're doing,
you could delete them manually.
But even if you took out the directory
that all the programs are in,
there's always extra files sitting around.
There's always statements
that you can win any files.
Certainly, you had Win 3.1 on your machine.
Especially with Win 3.1.
So that's where we have all these
commercial uninstall programs.
Now, sort of the mother of all uninstall
programs is called Uninstaller for MicroHelp.
You have that up here now?
We have it running here.
And what we're doing here is
we're actually in the process of
looking at a program that
we want to get rid of.
We want to get rid of, let's
say, not that we would want
to get it to Clarisworks.
We click on this.
We push Analyze.
And then the program would start
analyzing what it has to do.
And it would go ahead and not only delete
the files, but clean up the Win.i and i
program file and just get the machine
so it's as if that program were never there.
Now, eventually you're not going to need this,
because Windows 95
has an uninstall program built in.
But it only works with Windows 95 applications.
So for the present time, you're really
going to need a program like this.
Eventually,
it's going to be an operating system function.
So when you want to install Win 96, you'll
have the full little slider with Win 95.
Alright, last thing we hear, there are
special keyboards out now for Windows 95.
And we have one of them over here.
And show me what's so special about this.
Why might I want a separate
keyboard for Win 95?
Well, you don't need a separate keyboard.
I mean, you can function fine without one.
But we've got, for instance,
here's this little funny Windows key over here.
What does that do?
If you're buying a keyboard,
you get one of these and you push it.
And what it does is it
brings up the start menu.
It's just like if you'd press the start menu.
It just makes it easier.
And there's another one over on this side.
And what's that little one?
Well, it's programmable.
If it's just Microsoft, it does the same thing.
But in this particular one, it actually
brings up a special task switching menu
to make it just easier to change tasks.
And then we have another one here, which
is the same as pushing the right mouse button.
Oh, here we go.
It brought up another little window
just as if you'd pushed the right mouse button.
[...]
I mean, it's not essential,
but it makes it easier.
No, it makes it easier.
If you're buying a new keyboard,
it's something to look for.
All right.
Larry, thank you very much.
So let's say you decide to buy Windows 95.
There is a learning curve.
It's not the same as Windows 3.
1, certainly not the same as MS-DOS.
You have to figure out how to use it if
you're going to get your money's worth.
So let's take a look at your options
for getting up to speed on Windows 95.
The screens may look familiar,
but they are not quite the same.
There are new icons, new menus,
and there's a new way to organize files.
For a single user,
Windows 95 means establishing some new habits.
And for technical support staff,
it means answering a lot of questions.
One way to prepare yourself for the
changeover is to put the manual
aside and go back to school.
Windows 95 School.
So far, we've been focusing mostly on the
technical end of things because people
are just getting started in rolling out
Windows 95, and the companies are trying
to learn as much as they can
about how the operating system
works within their company.
So they're sending people to the technical
training classes in order to learn and
understand it very well before they go
ahead and give it to their end users.
The class approach appeals to people
who either don't have the time or
just don't like to read manuals.
It's kind of a shortcut to
the program's main features.
So even if you go through and you learn
it on your own, which I'm sure that lots
of people will probably have to do,
the tips, the tricks, things that will
ultimately save you time in the long stretch,
that's what you get out of class.
And the interaction between having someone
answer your questions as opposed to
you're having to either call support
hotline or trying to look it up through the
help screen, those are useful,
but again, they're time consuming.
So I think if you're looking for a
way to save time, come to class.
Classes are attractive for users who are
short on time and can afford the fees,
but for some brave souls, a book and
sheer persistence can accomplish the same
goals if they have the patience.
You get to know your computer a little
bit more because you're figuring out how
to set something up because
you're not just going to
set up Windows 95 on your computer.
You're going to set up all kinds of different
programs that you're going to need.
So it gave me like a sense of accomplishment
when I finally got it to work.
I was like jumping up and down and I was
all excited about it, but I think some
of the minuses is it can be very frustrating.
You know, when you have a question,
you have to refer to a book for an answer.
For the Computer Chronicles, I'm Giles Bateman.
[...]
Now the bottom line with any operating
system is what can you do with it?
How will it make your applications run better?
Just about every software maker is busy
cranking out new Win95 versions of their
programs, so you can take advantage
of the extra juice in Windows 95.
Here to show us two examples of brand
new Win95 apps are Jeff Rona of 3DI and
also over there Kevin Goldberg of Trimark.
Let's start with you, Jeff,
and you have a program called Trispectives.
And first of all, what's important
about Win95 to this 3D design program?
Well, our program really isn't able to
do anything without the power that's
behind a 32-bit application like Windows 95.
Its multi-threading capabilities allow
us to render faster, move objects
interactively quickly,
and overall speed performances that just
weren't available in Windows 3D.
You have some neat examples now,
so show us a little bit of
the program and what it does.
Right. We can actually create 3D models
interactively, and with the power of the
32-bit application,
we can continue moving those.
We have a 3D page that we've developed,
and on this 3D page, we can actually go
back in and show you some of the features
where we have in our graphics package.
We can do animation and
room design layout graphics
capabilities that you'd find in other packages.
Here we'll show you our
drag and drop animation.
We'll ship the product with over 1,000
IntelliShape 3D models, which are
like intelligent clip art.
We simply drag out of a catalog,
and the model is created
instantly and put into the scene.
So that's 3D clip art.
We call it IntelliShape.
They have intelligent properties. They know how
to land and slide over one another.
That makes it more intuitive
for a user in a drag and drop.
And the fact is you can animate
these things essentially.
Exactly. So now I'll just go into our
animation catalogs, make a spin move on
the Earth, and a spin move there.
We'll turn on our smart motions and click play,
and we have a real-time animation
sequence that can be exported
out to an AVI file if you wish.
We're using something like
PowerPoint or in Media Play.
What else can we do with this?
For many customers,
many people are working into virtual reality.
Here we've got a room scene that we've set up.
We can actually do a walk-through
camera angle to go into our room.
And we can turn ourselves
around so we get the back view.
And then for creation,
we can actually drag and drop more of those
models into this.
So we have a table and chair,
and the table knows
how to land on its legs,
and the chair knows how to land.
So that's the intelligent shape.
It knows where it belongs.
Exactly.
So even if we move it across the floor.
We can also position it using a new
feature we have called a tri-ball.
And here we'll just move the center,
and with just a simple mouse click, we can
actually replicate this three times
and create scenes very quickly.
Again, something you wouldn't really be
able to do in a non-32-bit application.
And we can save that scene out actually
as a VRML file or a Visual Basic Text
file for the models, AVI files,
JPEG, and the rest of the standards.
[...] the Spector's 3D design with the One 95.
Thanks a lot.
Alright,
let's see what Windows 95 does for a game now.
And I'll interrupt Kevin in
the middle of playing the
hive. And tell us about the game, Kevin.
Well, what Windows 95 gave us is the
ability to do pan-eractive sequences,
as well as streaming animation on top of them.
Something that we couldn't have done
before. And I'll jump right into gameplay here.
So tell us what's going on in the
game here while you're playing.
Well, I've just landed on an ocean platform,
and now I'm just going to
basically blow these guys away.
You can hear I'm doing pretty well.
This is a standard rail sequence
where your motion is predetermined.
And if you get far enough along, I'll be
able to show you a pan-eractive sequence
where you can stationary, and the sprites
move around you in the same way as
it's controlling the motion,
seamless branching between the two, and with
that Windows 95, you couldn't have done it.
Very cool. Alright, it's called the hive.
Absolutely. Thanks a lot.
Alright, you've no doubt heard about
the new Microsoft Network MSN,
which comes with Windows 95.
If you want help or more information on
Windows 95, there are, in fact, a lot
of online sites where you can find it.
So let's check out this week's
Net News with Giles Bateman.
Thanks, Stuart. I think the best place to
start is to go straight to the source.
Here I am at Microsoft's own Windows website,
and here I can get Windows 95
general information, tech information
and support, free software, and more.
But I think of more interest to online
users is the Microsoft Network.
If you have access to a web browser and
the Internet, you can actually check out
MSN before you ever sign up for it.
You just go to the MSN website,
and you can click About MSN, and, well, you can
learn what's on MSN today, and there are
more things you can do, but you can get
a general feel for it before
you ever become a member.
Now, if you're not on the Internet,
or perhaps you're on an online service and
you're not used to using the Internet,
remember the word Win News.
That's W-I-N-N-E-W-S. There are two N's
in the middle,
and there's no space in between it.
Now, in just about any service,
it's Go Win News or Jump Win News. I think only
on Genie you do a, what is it, Move to Page 95.
So that's the only one that's different.
The other thing you'll want to remember
is the Win 95L Mailing List.
Now, just follow the instructions you see here,
and you will get actual hard-core
hands-on information from
Windows 95 users themselves.
Now, time for our weekly summary of
what's new in the field of personal
computing. Let's go to Studio E
for this week's Computer News.
In the random access file this week,
it's a Pentium World. Computer Intelligence
InfoCorp reports that Pentiums now represent
53 percent of all new PCs sold. 486
-based PCs are dying out, and estimates
are that by December, 486s will account
for less than 25 percent of the market.
But just as the Pentium begins to dominate,
Intel has announced P6, the
next generation microprocessor.
They've given it an official name,
the Pentium Pro. P6
machines are due out later this year.
The Pentium Pro has five and a half
million transistors on the chip.
Compaq's new PCs are coming standard with
MPEG video capability. Compaq is also
bundling in 3D surround sound and a
speech recognition voicemail system.
IBM is also making its new Aptiva's more
multimedia-friendly. The new models just
out this week feature a special video
chip called M-Wave that also enables
smooth, full-motion video and duplex sound.
If you're looking for a Mac clone,
Power Computing has announced its first retail
deal for the Power100, one of the first
officially licensed Mac compatibles.
They'll be on sale at computer
city stores around the country.
In the fast-changing world of the internet,
domain names are no longer free.
Network Solutions, the company that
registers net domains, says effective
immediately, there will be a
$50 annual fee to register.
Domain names are being listed
at the rate of 14,000 a month.
Netscape says it will soon be out with
a new software package that makes it
easy to create your own webpage.
It's called Navigator Gold 2.0.
It will be available free on the net at the end
of October and will go on sale in January.
But two UC Berkeley graduate students
say they have found a security
gap in Netscape's web browser.
They say a knowledgeable
computer user can break their
existing security code in a minute.
Netscape has acknowledged the problem
and said a fix is on the way.
If you're trying to find a new CD-ROM
title and don't know where to look, check
out the new CD-ROM database on CompuServe.
The new section called CD-ROM-based
online lists nearly 10,000 current CD-ROM
titles, including description,
price, and publisher.
You may be using a Microsoft mouse or a
Microsoft keyboard, but now Gates and
company are getting into the joystick business.
MS has announced a new joystick
optimized for Windows 95.
It features eight buttons and
new digital optical technology
for faster response time.
It's called the Sidewinder 3D Pro
and it sells for under 60 bucks.
And finally, if you're really a geek,
check this out.
Website MorsePR.com. It will let you
follow brick by brick the construction of
Bill Gates' new $50 million mansion.
The website features aerial views of the
40,000 square foot home and detailed
shots of various parts of the house,
like the 50 car garage and the
underwater pool stereo system.
The page was put up by the
Morse MacFadden PR company.
Well, that's it for this week's Computer News.
Stewart?
Before we wrap things up, let me tell
you about one terrific program I found.
If you like computer games and you've
always wanted to write your own games, but
you don't have time to become a C++
programmer, there is a great package out
called Click and Play from an
English company named Europress.
This is a brilliant
object-oriented point-and-click
programming tool for game makers.
It comes with 10 games written in the
Click and Play language, and you can go
inside and see exactly how the games work,
and you can
modify them to suit your tastes.
This is one of the neatest software
packages I have come across in a long time.
Click and Play runs under Windows.
It sells for about $50, and
it's distributed by Maxis.
That's it for this week's Computer Chronicles.
We'll be back here next week with
another half hour of the latest
in personal computer technology.
I'm Stewart Chuffay.
We'll see you here next time.
Please, you're taking a close
look at remote management.
...insights and thoughts about the
fast-changing world of personal technology.
Videotapes and the Chuffay Letter can be
ordered by calling 1-800-800-9520, or by
writing us at the Computer Chronicles.